Guide to the Charles Hobson Collection, 1985-2008 M1555
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series XV. Magritte's Buckets, 1995
  Two pastel monotypes by Charles Hobson mounted in buckets made from board, copper, wire, brass tubing & bamboo, with small book. Subject is an outgrowth of navigation and surrealism project. In the search for a relationship between Rene Magritte and Isaac Hawkins, who thought you could calculate longitude at sea by measuring high and low tides. Several initial ideas were sketched out and later abandoned. A photograph in a book of Magritte's studio showed two buckets on the floor - used buckets as measuring devices. Edition of 10.
  - Design notes-Materials, invoices, fabrication notes, production photographs, sketch book drawings and 3/16/95 production drawing (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Final Production Patterns and Masters - typography, sample paper and photo copy transparencies (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Small Bucket Working Materials-Including monotypes and layout patterns (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Production Pieces-Extra labels and scroll papers (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Bucket Wrap Materials-Color photo copies and monotype ghosts. (Flat-box 16, Folder 13)
  - Prototypes - sample boxes and sample handle materials including bamboo and copper. (Flat-box 18, Folder 1)
- Series XVI. Man Ray's Kiss, 1995
  Pastel monotype by Charles Hobson and accordion book of handwritten text on hand-painted BFK Rives, together with metronome and small book describing relationship between John Harrison and Man Ray. Edition of 4 variations. Size: 9 x 5 x 5 inches.
  - Design notes (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Small Book Design (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Accordion Structure - patterns and samples, text, typography (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - Hinging Materials (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Man Ray's Kiss Titles (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Lips and Placement Patterns. Monotypes, etc (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - Extra Accordion Assembly Materials (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - Typography - layouts, trials, handwritten final type (Map-folder 19)
- Series XVII. The Mappist, 2006
  The Mappist, Barry Lopez's multi-layered short story, has been made into a limited edition of forty-eight copies in the summer and fall of 2005. Each book has been assembled using original USGS maps for the concertina binding and selected pages, and the cover has been wrapped with a reproduction of a 1911 map of Bogotá from the collection of the Library of Congress. The slipcase has been covered with wood-grained paper to suggest the map cabinet which plays a pivotal role in the story. A metal label holder acts as a spine label. The concertina binding, when looked at from the edge, takes on its own topography of mountains and valleys.
  Printed letterpress. Slipcase covered with wood grain paper and metal label holder. Edition of 48. 11 x 10 x 1.25 inches.
  - Pencil Images (Barry's Pencils): original monotypes, ghosts and digital print variations; digital photographs (Barry's writing studio). (Flat-box 28, Folder 1)
  - Corrugated Cover: design notes and cutting instructions; cutting jigs. (Flat-box 28, Folder 2)
  - Design Notes: sketchbook notations, assembly diagrams and sample papers. (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: permission letter from Barry Lopez, printing instructions, etc. (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Typography: proofs and correspondence with Les Ferriss. (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Hand Images: preliminary digital photographs, trials and transparencies (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Landscape Images: digital photos, monotypes and transparencies (Box 30, Folder 6-7)
  - Labels: water symbols, Jack Ranch labels (and location jig), topographic labels and magnetic North labels [not used] (Box 30, Folder 8-9)
  - Label Holder/Slipcase (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Concertina Design: master concertina fold directions (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Extra Production Materials: hand transparencies, landscape transparencies and USGS essay. (Box 30, Folder 12-13)
  - Bogotá Maps: Library of Congress copies (Map-folder 31)
  - Prototypes and display copies (4 folders, 1 prototype, 1 display copy) (Flat-box 32)
- Series XVIII. The Near Woods, 2006
  In the year 2000 Barry Lopez wrote an essay, The Near Woods, which described the elusive and magical space between the wild, deep woods and the civilized space of humans. Jerry Reddan, a master letterpress printer and typographic designer, came upon the essay and published it in a small edition of 165 copies in paper covers through his Tangram Press in 2005. He also printed and left unbound an additional twenty-six copies to be made into a special edition. The special edition has been designed by Charles Hobson and has been published by Pacific Editions in the summer of 2006 and is signed by the author and the artist.
  The special edition has been made with the image of a bear that folds out from the back page and has been reproduced as a digital pigment print on German Etching paper and has been hand-colored with pastel and acrylic paint by the artist. The book has been bound in boards and covered with a reproduction of “Dosiño del Rancho San Miguelito,” circa 1841, a drawing used to establish land grants in California and is reproduced with the kind permission of The Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley.
  - Design and assembly notes: working notes, binding details and jigs; prospectus design. (Flat-box 34, Folder 1)
  - Trial Etchings for Walking Bear: transparencies and proofs (Flat-box 34, Folder 2)
  - Digital Prints and Proofs: small walking bear, small standing bear, large bear (“Dream Bear”; 4 final images/one proof), cover Image (from Bancroft Library) 5 copies. (Flat-box 34, Folder 3)
  - Monotypes and Working Drawings: Standing Bear, Walking Bear and Bear Mouth (not used in edition) (Flat-box 34, Folder 4)
  - Trial Etchings for Walking Bear: copper plates (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
  - Trial Etchings for Standing Bear: copper plate and 2 proofs (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Book Cover Prototypes and Trials: 4 prototypes (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Labels and Extra End Papers: spine labels, title page labels, misc. small bear prints and extra end papers (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (Box 33, Folder 6)
- Series XIX. Parisian Encounters, 1992
  French door format book with monotype/pastel portraits of eight famous couples, who met in Paris, includes maps and eccentric biographies. Chronicle Books trade edition. Size: 6 x 11 inches.
  - Design Notes: a. Design drawings and diagrams; narrative detailing possible design layout and bibliography. b. Chronicle Book design description and related notes (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Research Files (files of biographical information about each of following): Napoleon/Josephine, Flaubert/Louise, Chopin/George Sand, Henry Miller/Anais Nin, Degas/Cassatt, Rodin/Camile Claudel, Pierre Curie, Madame Curie, Man Ray/Lee Miller. (Box 21, Folder 2-10)
  - Image Design (files relating to portraits and graphic elements for each): Napoleon, Josephine, Flaubert, Louise, Chopin, George Sand, Degas, Cassatt, Man Ray and Lee Miller. (Box 21, Folder 11-20)
  - Image Design (files relating to portraits and graphic elements for each): Henry Miller, Anais Nin, Rodin, Camile Claudel, Pierre Curie, Madame Curie. (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
  - Chronicle Book proofs (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Prototypes and progress proof photographs Disassembled book pages (possible display copies.) (Box 22, Folder 8-9)
  - Map research and details: including copyright clearance from Library of Congress, November 1993. (Box 22, Folder 10)
- Series XX. Poems from the Heart, 2004
  Poems from the Heart, 2004, is a hand-made artist's book picturing the heart sculpture made in connection with Hearts in San Francisco, a project benefiting the SF General Hospital. The book contains eighteen poems by children about love and the heart used on the sculptural heart. Each book has been hand-sewn into a painted cover and mounted in a folded corrugated folder. It contains digital pigment prints from an Epson 2200 printer. Edition of 150. 5.5 4.25 x .5 inches.
  - Book design notes: early prototypes, layout, notes on assembly time and photos. (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Heart Sculpture design notes: painted images (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Book prototypes: prototypes, extra cover images and sales display card (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Matrixes: cover, scoring board for cover and label placement (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Poems for transfer to altered books: camera ready copy (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper coverage (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Altered book with poems used on sculpture (see also Flat Box 23) (Box 22, Folder 17-19)
  - Altered book with poems used on sculpture (Flat-box 23)
- Series XXI. R.O.W., 2006
  R.O.W., a consideration of the right of way rules for sailing vessels, has been made as a limited edition artists' book in 2006. The central image in the book is a three foot square relief print which was created as part of a program at the San Francisco Center for the Book. It was originally printed in 2005 by a steamroller at Carolina and 16th Streets, San Francisco. Kay Bradner and Charles Hobson collaborated on the design of the print. Kay Bradner cut the linoleum block and printed the relief prints on Rives BFK 300 gm paper. Charles Hobson designed the book and assembled it with the assistance of Alice Shaw in an edition of 12 copies. It is covered in a transparent corrugated chemise which is closed with sailing line and a cleat.
  R.O.W. measures 18 by 9 inches closed and extends, when opened fully, to a length to 7 1/2 feet. Edition of 12.
  - R.O.W. general: research material, correspondence, estimates and design notes. (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Small drawings: original tracing paper drawings, proofs (some by Kay Bradner and some by Charles Hobson.) (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - R.O.W. small texts: texts as designed for window openings in the printed pages. (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Extra pieces and parts: small drawing cutouts and tabs for window images (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Patterns and matrixes: patterns and jigs used for assembling the edition. (Flat-box 25, Folder 1)
  - Extra pages, proofs and drafts: extra pages, extra page proofs, trial cover materials, cover drawings by Kay Bradner and extra hinges. (Flat-box 25, Folder 2)
  - Trial slipcase/chemise with cleat (artifact) (Flat-box 25, Folder 3)
- Series XXII. Seeing Stars, 2001
  Seeing Stars uses die cut cards, a flashlight and a small story book to introduce readers to several prominent constellations. Greek stargazers in the 4th century BC gave the names of characters in the Andromeda myth to six constellations clustered together near the North Star. A child can use the flashlight to shine the shape of each character's constellation on the ceiling, wall or table. Design inspired by Andromeda Imagined.
  - Text (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Chronicle Books box design (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Design proposal #1: original design proposal July, 1999. Sports figures and draft of text. (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Design proposal #2: second proposal to Chronicle Books November, 1999, including box design. (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and design proofs with Chronicle Books; including page proofs, color checks. October 2000-March 2001 (Box 24, Folder 9-10)
  - Project research: historical astronomy including research at Stanford's Green Library, photographs and photocopies. (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Early prototypes): two trial prototypes, one with sports figures, and 2nd proof from Chronicle Books. (Box 24, Folder 12-13)
  - Sample flashlight (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Star cut cards: early versions and final (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Drawings and outline drawings: early versions and final. (see also Box 26.1) (Flat-box 25, Folder 4)
  - Inkjet monotypes of constellations: figures for booklet (Flat-box 25, Folder 5)
  - Star cut cards: color proofs (Flat-box 25, Folder 6)
  - Star charts: versions for Chronicle Books (Flat-box 25, Folder 7)
  - Drawings and outline drawings: early versions and final (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Series XXIII. Shipwreck Stories, 1996
  Limited edition accordion book by Charles Hobson with seven photogravures, hand-colored charts, and Mylar drawings. Edition of 28. Size: 10-1/4 x 8-3/4 x 1 inches. Collage of facts, fictions, images and maritime charts to give different views of six shipwrecks that occurred between 1865 and 1944 along the Northern California coast.
  - Maritime charts: experimentations, designs with shipwreck icon and photocopy masters for printing on hand colored paper and copies of final maps. (Flat-box 25, Folder 8-9)
  - Original drawings for photogravures (Flat-box 25, Folder 10)
  - Photogravure proofs and final photogravure: Salvage; Ship at Cliff (two versions) (Flat-box 25, Folder 11)
  - Design and Research: binder with historical summaries, research notes and drafts of stories and alternative stories. Club paper for March 11, 1996. (Box 26, Folder 2-4)
  - Prototypes: including alternative page sizes and alternative layouts in black and white (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Binding Notes: including templates and assembly instructions and labels (Box 26, Folder 6-7)
  - Typography: early layouts, camera ready art and notes to printer (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Vellum tests and Mylar (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Cut Outs for tracing figures: various kinds of transparency and vellum for overlays with figures (Box 26, Folder 10-11)
  - Letters from Stockfleth's grand-daughter, Charmetta Mann: February 7, 2000 and May 11, 2008; includes genealogy, photocopies of photographs, clipping. (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Photogravure proofs: Brother Jonathan (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Prospectus: labels, design notes, assembly notes and photocopy masters. (see also Flat Box #28) (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Photogravure proofs and final photogravure: Lightning and Sunken Sails, Liberty Ship (Flat-box 28, Folder 3-4)
  - Page proofs: typography (two complete sets, mixed) (Flat-box 28, Folder 5)
  - Prospectus: design notes, assembly notes and photocopy masters (Flat-box 28, Folder 6)
- Series XXIV. A Supper in Montmartre, 1985
  A Supper in Montmartre was printed in a seminar class at UC Berkeley taught in the Bancroft Library's rare book. Five students printed this small single signature book on an 1857 Albion hand press.
  The text is a memoir by Harriet Lane Levy recounting the legendary dinner party given by Picasso for the artist Henri Rousseau in 1908. Part of the story involved the inebriated and frantic departure of the poet André Salmon, who had been Harriet's dinner partner. Intoxicated by her conversation and charm, as well as good French wine, he left the table in disarray and on his way out chewed off the roses on the stylish turban she'd worn that had been left outside the dining room door. The etching of an imagined turban and roses on an antique hat rack is the first illustration by Charles Hobson for a limited edition book.
  - Etching proofs-preparatory and final versions, six pencil drawings, one proof from plate #1, and six proofs from plate #2. (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Bancroftiana Newsletter April 1986: article on A Supper in Montmartre (2 copies) (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Additional artist proofs and final prints: one final prints on book paper 12 1/2” x 10”; six artist proofs on various handmade papers and in various sizes; one final print on book paper 10” x 21 1/2” (Flat-box 28, Folder 7)
  - Text/typography layout notes: page proofs done at Bancroft Library; variations; paper alternatives, labels (Flat-box 28, Folder 8)
- Series XXV. Taking Off Emily Dickinson's Clothes, 2002
  Taking Off Emily Dickinson's Clothes, poem by Billy Collins, has been made as a limited edition of thirty copies in the summer and fall of 2002. It employs buttons, ribbons, feathers and a pastel monotype by Charles Hobson. Charles Hobson and Alice Shaw assembled the pages and made the slipcase. John Demerritt covered the boards in Fabriano Roma and the text has been set in 14 pt. Spectrum and printed letterpress by M & H Type, San Francisco.
  Accordion binding. 8 1/2 x 7 x 1 inches (closed). Seven pages with hidden definitions and fold out stanza from an Emily Dickinson poem.
  - Design notes including various assembly instructions (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and permissions: letters requesting and granting permission to print with Billy Collins (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Prototype structures: five early design versions and prototypes (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Prototyping materials: buttons, hooks; Seam binding, elastic thread (Box 27, Folder 28)
  - Cover design: binder estimates, sample papers, hinges (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Feathers and button experiments/scans (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Templates: hinging and monotype placement. (see also map folder #29) (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Monotype designs: four monotypes and ink jet proofs and hand coloring information. (Flat-box 28, Folder 9)
  - Templates: hinging and monotype placement (Map-folder 29)
  - Extra letterpress typographic pages (Box 30, Folder 1)
- Series XXVI. Three Kisses, 2004
  Three Kisses is a handmade limited edition book that has been made from postcards, translucent envelopes, various papers and features the photographs of Robert Doisneau. Each envelope contains a photograph and a fictional story by Charles Hobson about the persons in the photographs. A pastel monotype by Charles Hobson has been reproduced as a digital pigment print with hand coloring. The book is bound as an accordion and has a corrugated board slipcase which measures 5 1/2 x 4 x 3/4 inches. Edition of 90 copies.
  - Design notes: including preliminary working materials from Arch (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Prototypes: three versions of book dummy (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Materials for Arch Design Project: sample postcards, envelopes and design instructions (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Monotype-"Last Kiss"/Smooch: first impression and ghost and digital proofs (Box 37, Folder 4-5)
  - Production Materials; including monotype print-outs, postcard kisses, spine labels, excess hinges and past-ins, accordion pages (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Title Page: layout and final versions (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Prospectus Design File and Materials (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Matrices: guides for cover, accordion and embossing guides (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Matrices: guides for cover, accordion and embossing guides. (Map-folder 39)
- Series XXVII. Variation on the Word SLEEP, 1991
  Margaret Atwood's poem accompanied by an accordion monotype by Charles Hobson, boxed in a black, lacquered wood box. Edition of 20. Size: 7-1/4 x 5-1/8 x 1 inches.
  - Design notes: photographs, text of poem and diagrams (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Typography: title page and sample printing (Box 37, Folder 11)
  - Monotypes: trials, four ghosts (two with hand coloring) and two counter proofs. (Flat-box 38, Folder 1)
  - Image design: pencil drawing, monotype key line on Mylar, folding matrix and reference photographs (Flat-box 38, Folder 2)
- Series XXVIII. The Writer, 2004
  A two-part limited edition artist's book inspired by Richard Wilbur's warm and gentle poem conveying a parent's respect and love for his child as she begins the voyage into adulthood. The two volumes are housed in a clamshell box with the larger volume containing the text of the poem set in 14-point courier and printed letterpress on BFK Rives paper. The smaller volume is a flip book, or rather a "flutter book," and contains selected words taken from the poem that reprise the poem with a new cadence. The edition in its box measures 12 x 12 x 1 1/4 inches. Edition of 54 copies.
  - Design notes, general; includes sketchbook pages, correspondence with binder, letterpress layouts (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Permissions: correspondence with Richard Wilbur and publisher; New Yorker article, Nov. 22, 2004 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Page proofs: letterpress proofs and unbound page proofs (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Polymer plates, typography (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Labels, titles and placement patterns for large book (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Inkjet monotype experiments: final image of starling in large book for vellum print (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - Starling cutouts (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - Flipbook design experiments and layout (Box 33, Folder 14-15)
  - Prospectus (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - Starling flight monotypes and experiments: original monotypes, hand colored inkjet prints and transparencies (Flat-box 34, Folder 5-6)
  - Flight sequence: experiments and bird cutouts (2 folders) (Flat-box 34, Folder 7-8)
  - Flipbook layout and cover (Flat-box 34, Folder 9)
  - Vellum trials and extras (Flat-box 34, Folder 10)
  - Prototypes (Flat-box 34, Folder 11)
  - Large books folding jig for inside cover (Map-folder 35)
- Series XXIX. Writing on the Body, 1999
  Writing on the Body has been made in a limited edition of forty-five copies in the summer and fall of 1999 with eight hand colored photogravure etchings from mixed media figure drawings by Charles Hobson combined with fragments of Degas's handwriting. Kay Bradner made the plates for the photogravures and editioned the etchings with Charles Hobson who hand colored the etchings with pastel. The text has been hand set with 12 point Méridien on BFK Rives by Jack W. Stauffacher at The Greenwood Press, San Francisco. John DeMerritt bound the book.
  - Subseries A. Design Materials
    Materials relating to the design and research aspects of the book.
    - Binding materials, spine and cover board matrix, matrix for cover paper (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Preliminary text layout (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Laser prints of drawings used in WOB (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - Preliminary dummy with Xerox and laser prints (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - Project notes/correspondence with binder and printer (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Sample paper and fabrics: sample fabrics: sample book cloth with silk-screen 13" x 2"; cover paper hand painted with Degas photocopy (3 copies) (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Xerox end paper proofs (9 copies) (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Silk-screen end papers (4 copies) (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Thank you letter from Jack Stauffacher dated 11/18/99. (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Article from Nob Hill Gazette article re: Jack Stauffacher, March 1999 (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Excerpt from magazine Typographie, Oct. 1997 about Meridien typeface (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Prospectus: Prospectus master materials and design matrix; Prospectus insert; Digital photos; Prospectus (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Degas handwriting and Mylar for etching overlays (Flat-box 38, Folder 3)
    - Typographic page proofs and corrections (Flat-box 38, Folder 4)
    - Blank typographic page proofs (15) (Flat-box 38, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B. Proofs and Plates, Centolella, Tom; Collins, Billy; DeMerritt, John; Evans, Kathy; Levy, Harriet Lane; Lopez, Barry; Mann, Charmetta; Shaw, Alice; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Wilbur, Richard
    Photogravure plates for various states of etchings for each work. Proofing was done by Kay Bradner and Charles Hobson over a period of several weeks, experimenting with color, cropping, and text overlay. Edition printing was done over a period of two weeks, with Kay doing the initial inking and Charles making final wiping adjustments and additions. In addition to the eight prints included in the book, three additional images were printed as possible alternatives for the design. 48 Trial Proofs and 42 plates and alternate plates from this process are included in the archive.
    Colet, Louise; Earhart, Amelia; Flaubert, Gustave; Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904; Artists' books; Artists' books--United States; Constellations--Artists' books; Copperplates; Longitude--Measurement-- Artists' books; Monotypes; Photogravure; Shipwrecks-- Artists' books; Typography
    - #1 Mystery, 3 plastic sleeves with 2 trial proofs and 3 plates, plus transparency, color notes, and inking notes
      - Plate #13; Trial Proof; Photogravure Gradient Strip (Box 41, Items 1, Sleeve 1)